<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Deep Learning on MLWhiz</title>
    <link>https://mlwhiz.com/tags/deep-learning/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Deep Learning on MLWhiz</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://mlwhiz.com/tags/deep-learning/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>NLP  Learning Series: Part 3 - Attention, CNN and what not for Text Classification</title>
      <link>https://mlwhiz.com/blog/2019/03/09/deeplearning_architectures_text_classification/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlwhiz.com/blog/2019/03/09/deeplearning_architectures_text_classification/</guid>
      <description>This post is the third post of the NLP Text classification series. To give you a recap, I started up with an NLP text classification competition on Kaggle called Quora Question insincerity challenge. So I thought to share the knowledge via a series of blog posts on text classification. The first post talked about the different preprocessing techniques that work with Deep learning models and increasing embeddings coverage. The second post, I talked through some basic conventional models like TFIDF, Count Vectorizer, Hashing, etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What my first Silver Medal taught me about Text Classification and Kaggle in general?</title>
      <link>https://mlwhiz.com/blog/2019/02/19/siver_medal_kaggle_learnings/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlwhiz.com/blog/2019/02/19/siver_medal_kaggle_learnings/</guid>
      <description>Kaggle is an excellent place for learning. And I learned a lot of things from the recently concluded competition on Quora Insincere questions classification in which I got a rank of 182/4037. In this post, I will try to provide a summary of the things I tried. I will also try to summarize the ideas which I missed but were a part of other winning solutions.
As a side note: if you want to know more about NLP, I would like to recommend this awesome course on Natural Language Processing in the Advanced machine learning specialization.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NLP  Learning Series: Part 2 - Conventional Methods for Text Classification</title>
      <link>https://mlwhiz.com/blog/2019/02/08/deeplearning_nlp_conventional_methods/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlwhiz.com/blog/2019/02/08/deeplearning_nlp_conventional_methods/</guid>
      <description>This is the second post of the NLP Text classification series. To give you a recap, recently I started up with an NLP text classification competition on Kaggle called Quora Question insincerity challenge. And I thought to share the knowledge via a series of blog posts on text classification. The first post talked about the various preprocessing techniques that work with Deep learning models and increasing embeddings coverage. In this post, I will try to take you through some basic conventional models like TFIDF, Count Vectorizer, Hashing etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NLP  Learning Series: Part 1 - Text Preprocessing Methods for Deep Learning</title>
      <link>https://mlwhiz.com/blog/2019/01/17/deeplearning_nlp_preprocess/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlwhiz.com/blog/2019/01/17/deeplearning_nlp_preprocess/</guid>
      <description>Recently, I started up with an NLP competition on Kaggle called Quora Question insincerity challenge. It is an NLP Challenge on text classification and as the problem has become more clear after working through the competition as well as by going through the invaluable kernels put up by the kaggle experts, I thought of sharing the knowledge.
Since we have a large amount of material to cover, I am splitting this post into a series of posts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Layman guide to moving from Keras to Pytorch</title>
      <link>https://mlwhiz.com/blog/2019/01/06/pytorch_keras_conversion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlwhiz.com/blog/2019/01/06/pytorch_keras_conversion/</guid>
      <description>Recently I started up with a competition on kaggle on text classification, and as a part of the competition, I had to somehow move to Pytorch to get deterministic results. Now I have always worked with Keras in the past and it has given me pretty good results, but somehow I got to know that the CuDNNGRU/CuDNNLSTM layers in keras are not deterministic, even after setting the seeds.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What Kagglers are using for Text Classification</title>
      <link>https://mlwhiz.com/blog/2018/12/17/text_classification/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlwhiz.com/blog/2018/12/17/text_classification/</guid>
      <description>With the problem of Image Classification is more or less solved by Deep learning, Text Classification is the next new developing theme in deep learning. For those who don&amp;rsquo;t know, Text classification is a common task in natural language processing, which transforms a sequence of text of indefinite length into a category of text. How could you use that?
 To find sentiment of a review. Find toxic comments in a platform like Facebook Find Insincere questions on Quora.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>