<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Deep Learning on MLWhiz</title>
    <link>mlwhiz.com/tags/deep-learning/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Deep Learning on MLWhiz</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 17 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="mlwhiz.com/tags/deep-learning/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>NLP  Learning Series: Text Preprocessing Methods for Deep Learning</title>
      <link>mlwhiz.com/blog/2019/01/17/deeplearning_nlp_preprocess/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>mlwhiz.com/blog/2019/01/17/deeplearning_nlp_preprocess/</guid>
      <description>Recently, I started up with an NLP competition on Kaggle called Quora Question insincerity challenge. It is an NLP Challenge on text classification and as the problem has become more clear after working through the competition as well as by going through the invaluable kernels put up by the kaggle experts, I thought of sharing the knowledge.
Since we have a large amount of material to cover, I am splitting this post into a series of posts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Layman guide to moving from Keras to Pytorch</title>
      <link>mlwhiz.com/blog/2019/01/06/pytorch_keras_conversion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>mlwhiz.com/blog/2019/01/06/pytorch_keras_conversion/</guid>
      <description>Recently I started up with a competition on kaggle on text classification, and as a part of the competition, I had to somehow move to Pytorch to get deterministic results. Now I have always worked with Keras in the past and it has given me pretty good results, but somehow I got to know that the CuDNNGRU/CuDNNLSTM layers in keras are not deterministic, even after setting the seeds.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What Kagglers are using for Text Classification</title>
      <link>mlwhiz.com/blog/2018/12/17/text_classification/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>mlwhiz.com/blog/2018/12/17/text_classification/</guid>
      <description>With the problem of Image Classification is more or less solved by Deep learning, Text Classification is the next new developing theme in deep learning. For those who don&amp;rsquo;t know, Text classification is a common task in natural language processing, which transforms a sequence of text of indefinite length into a category of text. How could you use that?
 To find sentiment of a review. Find toxic comments in a platform like Facebook Find Insincere questions on Quora.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>