<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Opinion on MLWhiz - Your Home for DS, ML, AI!</title><link>https://mlwhiz.com/tags/opinion/</link><description>Recent content in Opinion on MLWhiz - Your Home for DS, ML, AI!</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 13 Apr 2022 13:34:49 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://mlwhiz.com/tags/opinion/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>5 Essential Business-Oriented Critical Thinking Skills For Data Scientists</title><link>https://mlwhiz.com/blog/2020/08/12/ctskills/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mlwhiz.com/blog/2020/08/12/ctskills/</guid><description>&lt;p>As Alexander Pope said, to err is human. By that metric, who is more human than us data scientists? We devise wrong hypotheses constantly and then spend time working on them just to find out how wrong we were.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Don’t Democratize Data Science</title><link>https://mlwhiz.com/blog/2020/05/25/democratize/</link><pubDate>Mon, 25 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mlwhiz.com/blog/2020/05/25/democratize/</guid><description>&lt;p>Every few years, some academic and professional field gets a lot of cachet in the popular imagination. Right now, that field is data science. As a result, a lot of people are looking to get into it. Add to that the news outlets calling data science sexy and various academic institutes promising to make a data scientist out of you in just a few months, and you’ve got the perfect recipe for disaster.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Five Cognitive Biases In Data Science (And how to avoid them)</title><link>https://mlwhiz.com/blog/2020/05/25/cogbias/</link><pubDate>Mon, 25 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mlwhiz.com/blog/2020/05/25/cogbias/</guid><description>&lt;p>Recently, I was reading Rolf Dobell’s &lt;em>The Art of Thinking Clearly&lt;/em>, which made me think about cognitive biases in a way I never had before. I realized how deeply seated some cognitive biases are. In fact, we often don’t even consciously realize when our thinking is being affected by one. For data scientists, these biases can really change the way we work with data and make our day-to-day decisions, and generally not for the better.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Can AI help in fighting against Corona?</title><link>https://mlwhiz.com/blog/2020/03/24/coronaai/</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mlwhiz.com/blog/2020/03/24/coronaai/</guid><description>&lt;p>Feeling Helpless? I know I am.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With the whole shutdown situation, what I thought was once a paradise for my introvert self doesn’t look so good when it is actually happening.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>5 tips for getting your first Data Science job in 2020</title><link>https://mlwhiz.com/blog/2020/02/24/job/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mlwhiz.com/blog/2020/02/24/job/</guid><description>&lt;p>Many of my followers ask me — How difficult is it to get a job in the Data Science field? Or what should they study? Or what path they should take?&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>3 Mistakes you should not make in a Data Science Interview</title><link>https://mlwhiz.com/blog/2019/12/24/mistakes/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mlwhiz.com/blog/2019/12/24/mistakes/</guid><description>&lt;p>People ask me a lot about how to land a data science job? Or how to switch careers or how to study for a job interview?&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Top advice for a Data Scientist</title><link>https://mlwhiz.com/blog/2017/03/05/think_like_a_data_scientist/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mlwhiz.com/blog/2017/03/05/think_like_a_data_scientist/</guid><description>&lt;p>A data scientist needs to be Critical and always on a lookout of something that misses others. So here are some advices that one can include in day to day data science work to be better at their work:&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>