<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" >

  
  <channel>
    <title>Curated Resources on MLWhiz</title>
    <link>https://mlwhiz.com/tags/curated-resources/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Curated Resources on MLWhiz</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://mlwhiz.com/tags/curated-resources/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    

    

    <item>
      <title>Become an ML Engineer with these courses from Amazon and Google</title>
      <link>https://mlwhiz.com/blog/2020/08/27/mlengineercourses/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlwhiz.com/blog/2020/08/27/mlengineercourses/</guid>
      
      
      <media:content type="image/png" medium="image" width="700" height="400"
      url="https://mlwhiz.com/images/mlengineercourses/main.png"></media:content>
      

      
      <description>With ML Engineer job roles in all the vogue and a lot of people preparing for them, I get asked a lot of times by my readers to recommend courses for the ML engineer roles particularly and not for the Data Science roles.
Now, while both ML and Data Science pretty much have a high degree of overlap and I could very well argue that ML engineers do need to know many of the Data Science skills, there is a special place in hell reserved for ML engineers and that is the production and deployment part of the Data Science modeling process.</description>

      <content:encoded>  
        
        <![CDATA[  With ML Engineer job roles in all the vogue and a lot of people preparing for them, I get asked a lot of times by my readers to recommend courses for the ML engineer roles particularly and not for the Data Science roles.
Now, while both ML and Data Science pretty much have a high degree of overlap and I could very well argue that ML engineers do need to know many of the Data Science skills, there is a special place in hell reserved for ML engineers and that is the production and deployment part of the Data Science modeling process.
So, it doesn’t hurt to look at what two of the world’s biggest companies are looking at when it comes to ML engineering. These courses taught by Google and Amazon are rather popular and typically beginner level. So these are the best bet for people who are looking to start their journey to become an ML Engineer.
My main criteria for selecting these particular courses is the practical utility they provide as well as the pedigree they bring. Also, note that you don’t need to take these courses in any order or even take all of them. Just focus on one or two of them based on your particular requirements and you should be fine.
Google 1. Google IT Automation with Python Professional Certificate
Have you ever been asked to implement an API for your machine learning model, write some bash scripts to run a CRON job or some auto-scheduler and felt lost? This beginner-level professional certificate looks at Python from an engineering and production point of view rather than just Data Science. Something that we Data Scientists learn only after a few years of experience in the field and what is essentially a day to day thing for an MLE role.
The professional certificate from Google essentially talks about Python, Regex, Bash Scripting, automation testing, Github, debugging, Scaling up, and Programming Interfaces(APIs).
Most of these might not look so beginner-friendly right now, but they are some super cool skills to have in your portfolio and actually not that hard once you start understanding about the whole coding ecosystem.
2. Cloud Engineering with Google Cloud Professional Certificate
A lot of companies have started using Google Cloud Platform nowadays. If yours is such a company, this particular professional certificate might provide a lot of value. This specialization particularly focusses on the GCP platform and its various services like Google App Engine, Google Compute Engine, Google Kubernetes Engine, Google Cloud Storage, and BigQuery. You will also learn about other engineering concepts like load balancing, autoscaling, infrastructure automation, and managed services.
All of these services are pretty much becoming a standard for cloud computing at a lot of companies and it helps to learn about those if you are using the GCP infrastructure for building and deploying your models.
Amazon: 1. AWS Fundamentals
For people who aim to work at Amazon or the companies that use Amazon Web Services (AWS), this specialization teaches the AWS fundamentals and provides an overview of the features, benefits, and capabilities of AWS.
The main services you learn in this specialization are AWS Lambda(serverless compute), Amazon API Gateway(create, publish, maintain, monitor, and secure APIs at any scale), Amazon DynamoDB(Fast, flexible and scalable NoSQL database service), and Amazon Lex(Conversational AI for Chatbots), along with taking your application to the cloud.
This particular Amazon specialization is engineering heavy and by the end, you would understand how to build and deploy serverless applications with AWS.
2. Getting Started with AWS Machine Learning
There are a lot of things to consider while building a great machine learning system. We, as data scientists, only worry about the data and modeling part of the project but do we ever think about how we will deploy our models once we have them?
I have seen a lot of ML projects, and a lot of them are doomed to fail as they don’t have a set plan for production from the onset. Having a good platform and understanding how that platform deploys machine Learning apps will make all the difference in the real world. This course on AWS for implementing Machine Learning applications promises just that.
 This course will teach you:
1. How to build, train and deploy a model using Amazon SageMaker with built-in algorithms and Jupyter Notebook instance.
2. How to build intelligent applications using Amazon AI services like Amazon Comprehend, Amazon Rekognition, Amazon Translate and others.
— Source
 3. AWS Computer Vision: Getting Started with GluonCV
This course also provides an overview of Machine Learning with Amazon Web Services but with a specific emphasis on Computer Vision applications.
In this course, you will learn how to build and train a CV model using the Apache MXNet and GluonCV toolkit. The instructors start by discussing artificial neural networks and other deep learning concepts and then walk through how to combine neural network building blocks into complete computer vision models and train them efficiently.
This course covers AWS services and frameworks including Amazon Rekognition, Amazon SageMaker, Amazon SageMaker GroundTruth, Amazon SageMaker Neo, AWS Deep Learning AMIs via Amazon EC2, AWS Deep Learning Containers, and Apache MXNet on AWS.
This course will provide a lot of value to learners who want to train a deep learning vision model from scratch and deploy it efficiently using the AWS computing platform.
Conclusion In this post, I talked about the best courses I would recommend for people who are trying to get into ML engineering in this not so much return to school session.
Also, here are my course recommendations to become a Data Scientist in 2020.
I am going to be writing more beginner-friendly posts in the future too. Follow me up at Medium or Subscribe to my blog.
Also, a small disclaimer — There might be some affiliate links in this post to relevant resources, as sharing knowledge is never a bad idea.
]]>
        
      </content:encoded>
      
      
      
    </item>
    

    <item>
      <title>5 Online Courses you can take for free during COVID-19 Epidemic</title>
      <link>https://mlwhiz.com/blog/2020/03/27/covidcourses/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlwhiz.com/blog/2020/03/27/covidcourses/</guid>
      
      
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" medium="image" width="700" height="400"
      url="https://mlwhiz.com/images/covidcourses/main.jpeg"></media:content>
      

      
      <description>With Coronavirus on the prowl, there has been a huge demand across the world for MOOCs as schools and universities continue to shut down.
So, I find it great that providers like Coursera are hosting a lot of excellent courses on their site for free, but they are a little hard to find among all the paid courses.
While these courses are not providing verified certificates if you take them for free, in my view, it is the knowledge that matters than having a few certifications.</description>

      <content:encoded>  
        
        <![CDATA[  With Coronavirus on the prowl, there has been a huge demand across the world for MOOCs as schools and universities continue to shut down.
So, I find it great that providers like Coursera are hosting a lot of excellent courses on their site for free, but they are a little hard to find among all the paid courses.
While these courses are not providing verified certificates if you take them for free, in my view, it is the knowledge that matters than having a few certifications.
TLDR; With thousands of individuals laid off from this crisis, I believe it is crucial to get learning resources out now to people. So here is a list of courses that are great and free to learn.
1. Machine Learning Yes, you heard it right, Coursera is providing the Game Changer Machine Learning course by Andrew Ng for free right now.
As for my review, I think this is the one course that should be done by everyone interested in Machine Learning. For one, it contains the maths behind many of the Machine Learning algorithms and secondly Andrew Ng is a great instructor. Believe it or not, Andrew Ng not only taught but also motivated me to learn data science when I first started.
As for the curriculum, this course has a little of everything — Regression, Classification, Anomaly Detection, Recommender systems, Neural networks, plus a lot of great advice.
You might also want to go through a few of my posts while going through this course:
 The Hitchhiker’s Guide to Feature Extraction
 The 5 Classification Evaluation metrics every Data Scientist must know
 The 5 Feature Selection Algorithms every Data Scientist should know
 The Simple Math behind 3 Decision Tree Splitting criterions
  2. Algorithms Algorithms and data structures are an integral part of data science. While most of us data scientists don’t take a proper algorithms course while studying, they are essential all the same.
Many companies ask data structures and algorithms as part of their interview process for hiring data scientists.
They will require the same zeal to crack as your Data Science interviews, and thus, you might want to give some time for the study of algorithms and Data structure and algorithms questions.
This series of two courses offered by Robert Sedgewick covers all the essential algorithms and data structures. The first part of this course covers the elementary data structures, sorting, and searching algorithms, while the second part focuses on the graph and string-processing algorithms.
You might also like to look at a few of my posts while trying to understand some of the material in these courses.
 3 Programming concepts for Data Scientists A simple introduction to Linked Lists for Data Scientists Dynamic Programming for Data Scientists  3. Bayesian Statistics: From Concept to Data Analysis  “Facts are stubborn things, but statistics are pliable.” ― Mark Twain
 The war between a frequentist and bayesian is never over.
In this course, you will learn about MLE, priors, posteriors, conjugate priors, and a whole lot of other practical scenarios where we can use Bayesian Statistics. All in all, a well-packaged course which explains both frequentist and bayesian approach to statistics.
From the course website:
 This course introduces the Bayesian approach to statistics, starting with the concept of probability and moving to the analysis of data. We will compare the Bayesian approach to the more commonly-taught Frequentist approach, and see some of the benefits of the Bayesian approach.
 4. Practical Time Series Analysis Have you heard about ARIMA models, Stationarity in time series, etc. and have been boggled by these terms? This course aims to teach Time series from a fairly mathematical perspective. I was not able to find such a course for a fairly long time. And now it is free for all.
From the course website:
 In practical Time Series Analysis we look at data sets that represent sequential information, such as stock prices, annual rainfall, sunspot activity, the price of agricultural products, and more. We look at several mathematical models that might be used to describe the processes which generate these types of data
 If you want to use XGBoost or Tree-based models for time series analysis, do take a look at one of my previous post here:
 Using Gradient Boosting for Time Series prediction tasks  5. Getting Started with AWS for Machine Learning  The secret: it’s not what you know, it’s what you show.
 There are a lot of things to consider while building a great machine learning system. But often it happens that we, as data scientists, only worry about certain parts of the project.
But do we ever think about how we will deploy our models once we have them?
I have seen a lot of ML projects, and a lot of them are doomed to fail as they don’t have a set plan for production from the onset.
Having a good platform and understanding how that platform deploys machine Learning apps will make all the difference in the real world. This course on AWS for implementing Machine Learning applications promises just that.
 This course will teach you:
1. How to build, train and deploy a model using Amazon SageMaker with built-in algorithms and Jupyter Notebook instance.
2. How to build intelligent applications using Amazon AI services like Amazon Comprehend, Amazon Rekognition, Amazon Translate and others.
 You might also look at this post of mine, where I try to talk about apps and explain how to plan for Production.
 How to write Web apps using simple Python for Data Scientists? How to Deploy a Streamlit App using an Amazon Free ec2 instance? Take your Machine Learning Models to Production with these 5 simple steps  More Free Courses Also, don’t worry if you don’t want to learn the above ones. I have collected a list of some highly-rated courses that are free to audit before writing this post. You can download the excel file here. So have a stab at whatever you want to learn.
Continue Learning I am going to be writing more beginner-friendly posts in the future too. Follow me up at Medium or Subscribe to my blog.
Also, a small disclaimer — There might be some affiliate links in this post to relevant resources, as sharing knowledge is never a bad idea.
]]>
        
      </content:encoded>
      
      
      
    </item>
    

    <item>
      <title>Become a Data Scientist in 2020 with these 10 resources</title>
      <link>https://mlwhiz.com/blog/2020/02/21/ds2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlwhiz.com/blog/2020/02/21/ds2020/</guid>
      
      
      <media:content type="image/png" medium="image" width="700" height="400"
      url="https://mlwhiz.com/images/ds2020/main.png"></media:content>
      

      
      <description>I am a Mechanical engineer by education. And I started my career with a core job in the steel industry.
With those heavy steel enforced gumboots and that plastic helmet, venturing around big blast furnaces and rolling mills. Artificial safety measures, to say the least, as I knew that nothing would save me if something untoward happens. Maybe some running shoes would have helped. As for the helmet. I would just say that molten steel burns at 1370 degrees C.</description>

      <content:encoded>  
        
        <![CDATA[  I am a Mechanical engineer by education. And I started my career with a core job in the steel industry.
With those heavy steel enforced gumboots and that plastic helmet, venturing around big blast furnaces and rolling mills. Artificial safety measures, to say the least, as I knew that nothing would save me if something untoward happens. Maybe some running shoes would have helped. As for the helmet. I would just say that molten steel burns at 1370 degrees C.
As I realized based on my constant fear, that job was not for me, and so I made it my goal to move into the Analytics and Data Science space somewhere around in 2011. From that time, MOOCs have been my goto option for learning new things, and I ended up taking a lot of them. Good ones and bad ones.
Now in 2020, with the Data Science field changing so rapidly, there is no shortage of resources to learn data science. But that also often poses a problem for a beginner as to where to start learning and what to learn? There are a lot of great resources on the internet, but that means there are a lot of bad ones too.
 A lot of choices may often result in stagnation as anxiety is not good when it comes to learning.
 In his book, The Paradox of Choice — Why More Is Less, Schwartz argues that eliminating consumer choices can greatly reduce anxiety for shoppers. And the same remains true for Data Science courses as well.
This post is about providing recommendations to lost souls with a lot of choices on where to start their Data Science Journey.
1) Python 3 Programming Specialization  “GoodBye World” for Python 2.7!!!
 First, you need a programming language. This specialization from the University of Michigan is about learning to use Python and creating things on your own.
You will learn about programming fundamentals like variables, conditionals, and loops, and get to some intermediate material like keyword parameters, list comprehensions, lambda expressions, and class inheritance.
You might also like to go through my Python Shorts posts while going through this specialization.
Python Shorts Posts
2) Applied Data Science with Python  Do first, understand later
 We need to get a taste of Machine Learning before understanding it fully.
This specialization in Applied Data Science with Python gives an intro to many modern machine learning methods that you should know about. Not a thorough grinding, but you will get the tools to build your models.
 This skills-based specialization is intended for learners who have a basic python or programming background, and want to apply statistical, machine learning, information visualization, text analysis, and social network analysis techniques through popular python toolkits such as pandas, matplotlib, scikit-learn, nltk, and networkx to gain insight into their data.
 You might also like to go through a few of my posts while going through this specialization:
 Minimal Pandas Subset for Data Scientists
 Python’s One Liner graph creation library with animations Hans Rosling Style
 3 Awesome Visualization Techniques for every dataset
  3) Machine Learning Theory and Fundamentals After doing these above courses, you will gain the status of what I would like to call a “Beginner.”
Congrats!!!. You know stuff; you know how to implement things.
 You are Useful
 Yet, you do not fully understand all the math and grind that goes behind all these models.
You need to understand what goes behind the clf.fit. Its time to face the music. Nobody is going to take you seriously till you understand the Math behind your models.
 If you don’t understand it you won’t be able to improve it
 Here comes the Game Changer Machine Learning course. It contains the maths behind many of the Machine Learning algorithms.
I will put this course as the one course you have to take as this course motivated me into getting into this field, and Andrew Ng is a great instructor. Also, this was the first course that I took myself when I started.
This course has a little of everything — Regression, Classification, Anomaly Detection, Recommender systems, Neural networks, plus a lot of great advice.
You might also want to go through a few of my posts while going through this course:
 The Hitchhiker’s Guide to Feature Extraction
 The 5 Classification Evaluation metrics every Data Scientist must know
 The 5 Feature Selection Algorithms every Data Scientist should know
 The Simple Math behind 3 Decision Tree Splitting criterions
  4) Learn Statistical Inference  “Facts are stubborn things, but statistics are pliable.”― Mark Twain
 Mine Çetinkaya-Rundel teaches this course on Inferential Statistics. And it cannot get simpler than this one.
She is a great instructor and explains the fundamentals of Statistical inference nicely — a must-take course.
You will learn about hypothesis testing, confidence intervals, and statistical inference methods for numerical and categorical data.
You might also want to go through a few of my posts while going through this specialization:
 P-value Explained Simply for Data Scientists Confidence Intervals Explained Simply for Data Scientists  5) Learn SQL Basics for Data Science  SQL is the heart of all data ETL
 While we feel much more accomplished by creating models and coming up with the different hypotheses, the role of data munging can’t be understated.
And with the ubiquitousness of SQL when it comes to ETL and data preparation tasks, everyone should know a little bit of it to at least be useful.
SQL has also become a de facto standard of working with Big Data Tools like Apache Spark. This SQL specialization from UC Davis will teach you about SQL as well as how to use SQL for distributed computing.
From the Course website:
 Through four progressively more difficult SQL projects with data science applications, you will cover topics such as SQL basics, data wrangling, SQL analysis, AB testing, distributed computing using Apache Spark, and more
 You might also want to go through a few of my posts while going through this specialization:
 Learning SQL the Hard Way The Hitchhikers guide to handle Big Data using Spark 5 Ways to add a new column in a PySpark Dataframe  6) Advanced Machine Learning  In the big leagues, there is no spoonfeeding.
 You might not agree to this, but till now, whatever we have done has been spoonfed learning. The material was structured, and the Math has been minimal. But that has prepared you for the next steps. This Advanced Machine Learning specialization by Top Kaggle machine learning practitioners and CERN scientists takes another approach to learning by going through a lot of difficult concepts and guiding you through how things worked in the past and the most recent advancements in the Machine Learning World. The description on the website says:
 This specialization gives an introduction to deep learning, reinforcement learning, natural language understanding, computer vision and Bayesian methods. Top Kaggle machine learning practitioners and CERN scientists will share their experience of solving real-world problems and help you to fill the gaps between theory and practice.
 You might like to look at a few of my posts while trying to understand some of the material in this course.
 MCMC Intuition for Everyone NLP Learning Series  7) Deep Learning  Deep Learning is the Future
 Andrew NG is back again with his new Deep Learning Specialization. And this is Pure Gold.
Andrew Ng has achieved mastery in explaining difficult concepts in an easy to understand way. The nomenclature he follows is different from all other tutorials and courses on the net, and I hope it catches on as it is pretty helpful in understanding all the basic concepts.
From the specialization website:
 Learn the foundations of Deep Learning, understand how to build neural networks, and learn how to lead successful machine learning projects. You will learn about Convolutional networks, RNNs, LSTM, Adam, Dropout, BatchNorm, Xavier/He initialization, and more. You will work on case studies from healthcare, autonomous driving, sign language reading, music generation, and natural language processing.
 You might like to look at a few of my posts while trying to understand some of the material in this course.
 An End to End Introduction to GANs Object Detection using Deep Learning Approaches: An End to End Theoretical Perspective  8) Pytorch  Python on Fire
 I usually never advocate to learn a tool, but here I do. The reason being that it is incredible and seriously, you will be able to read code in a lot of recent research papers if you understand Pytorch. Pytorch has become a default programming language for researchers working in Deep Learning, and it will only pay for us to learn it.
A structured way to learn Pytorch is by taking this course on Deep Neural Networks with Pytorch. From the course website:
 The course will start with Pytorch’s tensors and Automatic differentiation package. Then each section will cover different models starting off with fundamentals such as Linear Regression, and logistic/softmax regression. Followed by Feedforward deep neural networks, the role of different activation functions, normalization and dropout layers. Then Convolutional Neural Networks and Transfer learning will be covered. Finally, several other Deep learning methods will be covered.
 You might also look at this post of mine, where I try to explain how to work with PyTorch. - Moving from Keras to Pytorch
9) Getting Started with AWS for Machine Learning  The secret: it’s not what you know, it’s what you show.
 There are a lot of things to consider while building a great machine learning system. But often it happens that we, as data scientists, only worry about certain parts of the project.
But do we ever think about how we will deploy our models once we have them?
I have seen a lot of ML projects, and a lot of them are doomed to fail as they don’t have a set plan for production from the onset.
Having a good platform and understanding how that platform deploys machine Learning apps will make all the difference in the real world. This course on AWS for implementing Machine Learning applications promises just that.
 This course will teach you: 1. How to build, train and deploy a model using Amazon SageMaker with built-in algorithms and Jupyter Notebook instance. 2. How to build intelligent applications using Amazon AI services like Amazon Comprehend, Amazon Rekognition, Amazon Translate and others.
 You might also look at this post of mine, where I try to talk about apps and explain how to plan for Production.
 How to write Web apps using simple Python for Data Scientists? How to Deploy a Streamlit App using an Amazon Free ec2 instance? Take your Machine Learning Models to Production with these 5 simple steps  10) Data Structures and Algorithms  Algorithms. Yes, you need them.
 Algorithms and data structures are an integral part of data science. While most of us data scientists don’t take a proper algorithms course while studying, they are essential all the same.
Many companies ask data structures and algorithms as part of their interview process for hiring data scientists.
They will require the same zeal to crack as your Data Science interviews, and thus, you might want to give some time for the study of algorithms and Data structure and algorithms questions.
One of the best resources I found to learn algorithms is the Algorithm Specialization on Coursera by UCSanDiego. From the specialization website:
 You will learn algorithmic techniques for solving various computational problems and will implement about 100 algorithmic coding problems in a programming language of your choice. No other online course in Algorithms even comes close to offering you a wealth of programming challenges that you may face at your next job interview.
 You might also like to look at a few of my posts while trying to understand some of the material in this specialization.
 3 Programming concepts for Data Scientists A simple introduction to Linked Lists for Data Scientists Dynamic Programming for Data Scientists -Handling Trees in Data Science Algorithmic Interview  Continue Learning I am going to be writing more beginner-friendly posts in the future too. Follow me up at Medium or Subscribe to my blog.
Also, a small disclaimer — There might be some affiliate links in this post to relevant resources, as sharing knowledge is never a bad idea.
]]>
        
      </content:encoded>
      
      
      
    </item>
    

    <item>
      <title>How did I learn Data Science?</title>
      <link>https://mlwhiz.com/blog/2019/08/12/resources/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlwhiz.com/blog/2019/08/12/resources/</guid>
      
      
      <media:content type="image/png" medium="image" width="700" height="400"
      url="https://mlwhiz.com/images/resources/1.png"></media:content>
      

      
      <description>I am a Mechanical engineer by education. And I started my career with a core job in the steel industry.
But I didn’t like it and so I left that.
I made it my goal to move into the analytics and data science space somewhere around in 2013. From then on, it has taken me a lot of failures and a lot of efforts to shift.
Now, people on social networks ask me how I got started in the data science field.</description>

      <content:encoded>  
        
        <![CDATA[  I am a Mechanical engineer by education. And I started my career with a core job in the steel industry.
But I didn’t like it and so I left that.
I made it my goal to move into the analytics and data science space somewhere around in 2013. From then on, it has taken me a lot of failures and a lot of efforts to shift.
Now, people on social networks ask me how I got started in the data science field. So I thought of giving a definitive answer.
 It is not really impossible to do this but it will take a lot of time and effort. Fortunately, I had an ample supply of both.
 Given below is the way that I took, and any aspiring person could choose to become a self-trained data scientist.
Some of the courses are not the same I did since some of them don’t exist and some have been merged into bigger specializations. But I have tried to keep it as similar to my experience as possible.
Also, I hope that you don’t lose hope after seeing the long list. You have to start with one or two courses. The rest will follow with time. Remember we have ample time.
Follow in order. I have tried to include everything that comes to my mind, including some post links which I think could be beneficial.
Introduction to Probability and Statistics Stat 110: The quintessential Probability and Statistics course you gotta take. All the lectures and notes are available on Youtube and his site for free.
If not for the content then for Prof. Joseph Blitzstein sense of humor. The above picture is a testament to that.
I took this course to enhance my understanding of probability distributions and statistics, but this course taught me a lot more than that.
Apart from Learning to think conditionally, this also taught me how to explain difficult concepts with a story.
This is a challenging class for a beginner but most definitely fun. The focus was not only on getting Mathematical proofs but also on understanding the intuition behind them and how intuition can help in deriving the proofs quickly. Sometimes the same proof was done in different ways to facilitate the learning of a concept.
One of the things I liked most about this course is the focus on concrete examples while explaining abstract concepts.
The inclusion of Gambler’s Ruin Problem, Matching Problem, Birthday Problem, Monty Hall, Simpsons Paradox, St. Petersberg Paradox, etc. made this course much much more exciting and enjoyable than any ordinary Statistics Course.
It will help you understand Discrete (Bernoulli, Binomial, Hypergeometric, Geometric, Negative Binomial, FS, Poisson) and Continuous (Uniform, Normal, expo, Beta, Gamma) Distributions.
He has also got a textbook based on this course, which is an excellent text and a must for any bookshelf.
 
Introduction to Python and Data Science:  Do first, understand later
 We need to get a taste of machine learning before understanding it fully. This segment is made up of three parts. These are not the exact courses I took to learn Python and getting an intro to data science. But they are quite similar and they serve the purpose.
a) Introduction to Data Science in Python This course is about learning to use Python and creating things on your own. You will learn about Python Libraries like Numpy, Pandas for data science.
You might also like my posts on Minimal Pandas for Data Scientists and small shorts on advanced python while going through this course.
Course description from Website:
 This course will introduce the learner to the basics of the python programming environment, including fundamental python programming techniques such as lambdas, reading and manipulating csv files, and the numpy library. The course will introduce data manipulation and cleaning techniques using the popular python pandas data science library and introduce the abstraction of the Series and DataFrame as the central data structures for data analysis, along with tutorials on how to use functions such as groupby, merge, and pivot tables effectively. By the end of this course, students will be able to take tabular data, clean it, manipulate it, and run basic inferential statistical analyses.
 b) Applied Machine Learning in Python This course gives an intro to many modern machine learning methods that you should know about. Not a thorough grinding but you will get the tools to build your own models. You will learn scikit-learn, which is the python library to create all sorts of models.
The focus here is to start creating things as soon as possible. No one likes to wait too long to get something useful, and you will become useful after this course.
 This course will introduce the learner to applied machine learning, focusing more on the techniques and methods than on the statistics behind these methods. The course will start with a discussion of how machine learning is different than descriptive statistics, and introduce the scikit learn toolkit through a tutorial.
 c) Visualizations  A well made visualization is worth more than any PPT
 One thing you also need to learn about is Visualizations. This is an area which is constantly evolving with a lot of new libraries coming frequently. The libraries I use most are Seaborn and Plotly.
You could take a look at the below posts to get started with both basic and advanced visualizations.
Python’s One-Liner graph creation library with animations Hans Rosling Style
3 Awesome Visualization Techniques for every dataset
Machine Learning Fundamentals After doing these above courses, you will gain the status of what I would like to call a “Beginner.”
Congrats!!!. You know stuff; you know how to implement things.
Yet you do not fully understand all the math and grind that goes behind all these models.
You need to understand what goes behind the clf.fit
 If you don’t understand it you won’t be able to improve it
 Here comes the Game Changer Machine Learning course. Contains the maths behind many of the Machine Learning algorithms.
I will put this course as the one course you gotta take as this course motivated me into getting in this field, and Andrew Ng is a great instructor. Also, this was the first course that I took myself when I started.
This course has a little of everything — Regression, Classification, Anomaly Detection, Recommender systems, Neural networks, plus a lot of great advice.
After this one, you are done with the three musketeers of the trade.
You know Python, you understand Statistics, and you have gotten the taste of the math behind ML approaches. Now it is time for the new kid on the block. D’artagnan. This kid has skills. While the three musketeers are masters in their trade, this guy brings qualities that add a new freshness to our data science journey.
Here comes Big Data for you.
Big Data Analytics Using Spark  Big Data is omnipresent. Deal with it.
 The whole big data ecosystem has changed a lot since the time I learned Hadoop. And Spark was the new kid on the block at that time. Those days…
The courses I took are pretty redundant as of now so I would try to recommend something suitable for this era. The best course I could find that embodies most of what I learned through scattered sources is Big Data Analytics Using Spark.
From the course website, after doing this course, you will learn:
 Programming Spark using Pyspark Identifying the computational tradeoffs in a Spark application Performing data loading and cleaning using Spark and Parquet Modeling data through statistical and machine learning methods  You could also take a look at my recent post on Spark.
The Hitchhikers guide to handle Big Data using Spark
Understand Linux Shell Not a hard requirement but a good to have skill. Shell is a big friend of data scientists. It allows you to do simple data-related tasks in the terminal itself. I couldn’t emphasize how much time shell saves for me every day.
You can read the below post by me to know about this: Impress Onlookers with your newly acquired Shell Skills
If you would like to take a course, you can look at The UNIX workbench course on Coursera.
Congrats you are a “Hacker” now.
 You have got all the main tools in your belt to be a data scientist.
 On to more advanced topics. From here, it depends on you what you want to learn.
You may want to take a totally different approach than what I took going from here. There is no particular order. “All Roads Lead to Rome” as long as you are moving.
Learn Statistical Inference Mine Çetinkaya-Rundel teaches this course on Inferential Statistics. And it cannot get simpler than this one.
She is a great instructor and explains the fundamentals of Statistical inference nicely — a must-take course.
You will learn about hypothesis testing, confidence intervals, and statistical inference methods for numerical and categorical data.
Deep Learning  It is all about layers
 Intro — Making neural nets uncool again. This is a code-first class for neural nets. An excellent Deep learning class from Kaggle Master Jeremy Howard. Entertaining and enlightening at the same time.
Advanced — You can try out this Deep Learning Specialization by Andrew Ng again. Pure Gold.
Advanced Math Book — A math-intensive book by Yoshua Bengio &amp;amp; Ian Goodfellow
Take a look at below post if you want to learn Pytorch.
Moving from Keras to Pytorch
Learn NLP, Use Deep Learning with Text and create Chatbots  Reading is overrated. Let the machine do it.
 Natural Language Processing is something which captured my attention a while back.
I wrote a series of 6 posts on it. If you want, you can take a look.
NLP Learning Series — Towards Data Science
Algorithms, Graph Algorithms, and More  Algorithms. Yes, you need them.
 Apart from that if you want to learn about Python and the underlying intricacies of the language you can take the Computer Science Mini Specialization from RICE university too.
This is a series of 6 short but good courses.
I worked on these courses as Data science will require you to do a lot of programming. And the best way to learn to program is by doing it.
The lectures are good, but the problems and assignments are awesome. If you work on this, you will learn Object-Oriented Programming, Graph algorithms, and creating games in Python. Pretty cool stuff.
You could also take a look at:
The 5 Feature Selection Algorithms every Data Scientist should know
The 5 Sampling Algorithms every Data Scientist need to know
Some Advanced Math Topics  Math — The power behind it all
 I am writing it last here but don’t underestimate the importance of Math in Data Science. You might want to look a little into these courses if you want to refresh your concepts.
Linear Algebra By Gilbert Strang— A Great Class by a great Teacher. I would definitely recommend this class to anyone who wants to learn Linear Algebra.
Multivariate Calculus — MIT Open Courseware
Convex Optimization — a MOOC on optimization from Stanford, by Steven Boyd, an authority on the subject.
Conclusion The Machine learning field is evolving, and new advancements are made every day. That’s why I didn’t put the third tier.
 The maximum I can call myself is a “Hacker,” and my learning continues.
 Everyone has their own path, and here I provided mine to become a data scientist. And this is in no way perfect as obviously, a lot of things can be added to it.
Though I did not complete any professional training, I consider myself more of a Computer science engineer than a mechanical engineer now due to the above courses.
I hope they help you too.
Thanks for the read. I am going to be writing more beginner-friendly posts in the future too. Follow me up at Medium or Subscribe to my blog.
]]>
        
      </content:encoded>
      
      
      
    </item>
    

    <item>
      <title>Top Data Science Resources on the Internet right now</title>
      <link>https://mlwhiz.com/blog/2017/03/26/top_data_science_resources_on_the_internet_right_now/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlwhiz.com/blog/2017/03/26/top_data_science_resources_on_the_internet_right_now/</guid>
      
      

      
      <description>I have been looking to create this list for a while now. There are many people on quora who ask me how I started in the data science field. And so I wanted to create this reference.
To be frank, when I first started learning it all looked very utopian and out of the world. The Andrew Ng course felt like black magic. And it still doesn&amp;amp;rsquo;t cease to amaze me.</description>

      <content:encoded>  
        
        <![CDATA[  I have been looking to create this list for a while now. There are many people on quora who ask me how I started in the data science field. And so I wanted to create this reference.
To be frank, when I first started learning it all looked very utopian and out of the world. The Andrew Ng course felt like black magic. And it still doesn&amp;rsquo;t cease to amaze me. After all, we are predicting the future. Take the case of Nate Silver - What else can you call his success if not Black Magic?
But it is not magic. And this is a way an aspiring guy could take to become a self-trained data scientist. Follow in order. I have tried to include everything that comes to my mind. So here goes:
1. Stat 110: Introduction to Probability: Joe Blitzstein - Harvard University The one stat course you gotta take. If not for the content then for Prof. Blitzstein sense of humor. I took this course to enhance my understanding of probability distributions and statistics, but this course taught me a lot more than that. Apart from Learning to think conditionally, this also taught me how to explain difficult concepts with a story.
This was a Hard Class but most definitely fun. The focus was not only on getting Mathematical proofs but also on understanding the intuition behind them and how intuition can help in deriving them more easily. Sometimes the same proof was done in different ways to facilitate learning of a concept.
One of the things I liked most about this course is the focus on concrete examples while explaining abstract concepts. The inclusion of ** Gambler’s Ruin Problem, Matching Problem, Birthday Problem, Monty Hall, Simpsons Paradox, St. Petersberg Paradox ** etc. made this course much much more exciting than a normal Statistics Course.
It will help you understand Discrete (Bernoulli, Binomial, Hypergeometric, Geometric, Negative Binomial, FS, Poisson) and Continuous (Uniform, Normal, expo, Beta, Gamma) Distributions and the stories behind them. Something that I was always afraid of.
He got a textbook out based on this course which is clearly a great text:
 2. Data Science CS109: - Again by Professor Blitzstein. Again an awesome course. Watch it after Stat110 as you will be able to understand everything much better with a thorough grinding in Stat110 concepts. You will learn about Python Libraries like Numpy,Pandas for data science, along with a thorough intuitive grinding for various Machine learning Algorithms. Course description from Website:
Learning from data in order to gain useful predictions and insights. This course introduces methods for five key facets of an investigation: data wrangling, cleaning, and sampling to get a suitable data set; data management to be able to access big data quickly and reliably; exploratory data analysis to generate hypotheses and intuition; prediction based on statistical methods such as regression and classification; and communication of results through visualization, stories, and interpretable summaries.  3. CS229: Andrew Ng After doing these two above courses you will gain the status of what I would like to call a &amp;ldquo;Beginner&amp;rdquo;. Congrats!!!. You know stuff, you know how to implement stuff. Yet you do not fully understand all the math and grind that goes behind all this.
Here comes the Game Changer machine learning course. Contains the maths behind many of the Machine Learning algorithms. I will put this course as the one course you gotta take as this course motivated me into getting in this field and Andrew Ng is a great instructor. Also this was the first course that I took.
Also recently Andrew Ng Released a new Book. You can get the Draft chapters by subcribing on his website here.
You are done with the three musketeers of the trade. You know Python, you understand Statistics and you have gotten the taste of the math behind ML approaches. Now it is time for the new kid on the block. D&amp;rsquo;artagnan. This kid has skills. While the three musketeers are masters in their trade, this guy brings qualities that adds a new freshness to our data science journey. Here comes Big Data for you.
4. Intro to Hadoop &amp;amp; Mapreduce - Udacity Let us first focus on the literal elephant in the room - Hadoop. Short and Easy Course. Taught the Fundamentals of Hadoop streaming with Python. Taken by Cloudera on Udacity. I am doing much more advanced stuff with python and Mapreduce now but this is one of the courses that laid the foundation there.
Once you are done through this course you would have gained quite a basic understanding of concepts and you would have installed a Hadoop VM in your own machine. You would also have solved the Basic Wordcount Problem. Read this amazing Blog Post from Michael Noll: Writing An Hadoop MapReduce Program In Python - Michael G. Noll. Just read the basic mapreduce codes. Don&amp;rsquo;t use Iterators and Generators yet. This has been a starting point for many of us Hadoop developers.
Now try to solve these two problems from the CS109 Harvard course from 2013:
A. First, grab the file word_list.txt from here. This contains a list of six-letter words. To keep things simple, all of the words consist of lower-case letters only.Write a mapreduce job that finds all anagrams in word_list.txt.
B. For the next problem, download the file baseball_friends.csv. Each row of this csv file contains the following:
 A person&amp;rsquo;s name The team that person is rooting for &amp;ndash; either &amp;ldquo;Cardinals&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Red Sox&amp;rdquo; A list of that person&amp;rsquo;s friends, which could have arbitrary length  For example: The first line tells us that Aaden is a Red Sox friend and he has 65 friends, who are all listed here. For this problem, it&amp;rsquo;s safe to assume that all of the names are unique and that the friendship structure is symmetric (i.e. if Alannah shows up in Aaden&amp;rsquo;s friends list, then Aaden will show up in Alannah&amp;rsquo;s friends list). Write an mr job that lists each person&amp;rsquo;s name, their favorite team, the number of Red Sox fans they are friends with, and the number of Cardinals fans they are friends with.
Try to do this yourself. Don&amp;rsquo;t use the mrjob (pronounced Mr. Job) way that they use in the CS109 2013 class. Use the proper Hadoop Streaming way as taught in the Udacity class as it is much more customizable in the long run.
If you are done with these, you can safely call yourself as someone who could &amp;ldquo;think in Mapreduce&amp;rdquo; as how people like to call it.Try to do groupby, filter and joins using Hadoop. You can read up some good tricks from my blog:
Hadoop Mapreduce Streaming Tricks and Techniques
If you are someone who likes learning from a book you can get: 
5. Spark - In memory Big Data tool. Now comes the next part of your learning process. This should be undertaken after a little bit of experience with Hadoop. Spark will provide you with the speed and tools that Hadoop couldn&amp;rsquo;t.
Now Spark is used for data preparation as well as Machine learning purposes. I would encourage you to take a look at the series of courses on edX provided by Berkeley instructors. This course delivers on what it says. It teaches Spark. Total beginners will have difficulty following the course as the course progresses very fast. That said anyone with a decent understanding of how big data works will be OK.
Data Science and Engineering with Apache® Spark™
I have written a little bit about Basic data processing with Spark here. Take a look: Learning Spark using Python: Basics and Applications
Also take a look at some of the projects I did as part of course at github
If you would like a book to read: 
If you don&amp;rsquo;t go through the courses, try solving the same two problems above that you solved by Hadoop using Spark too. Otherwise the problem sets in the courses are more than enough.
6. Understand Linux Shell: Shell is a big friend for data scientists. It allows you to do simple data related tasks in the terminal itself. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t emphasize how much time shell saves for me everyday.
Read these tutorials by me for doing that:
Shell Basics every Data Scientist Should know -Part I Shell Basics every Data Scientist Should know - Part II(AWK)
If you would like a course you can go for this course on edX.
If you want a book, go for:
 Congrats you are an &amp;ldquo;Hacker&amp;rdquo; now. You have got all the main tools in your belt to be a data scientist. On to more advanced topics. From here it depends on you what you want to learn. You may want to take a totally different approach than what I took going from here. There is no particular order. &amp;ldquo;All Roads lead to Rome&amp;rdquo; as long as you are running.
7. Learn Statistical Inference and Bayesian Statistics I took the previous version of the specialization which was a single course taught by Mine Çetinkaya-Rundel. She is a great instrucor and explains the fundamentals of Statistical inference nicely. A must take course. You will learn about hypothesis testing, confidence intervals, and statistical inference methods for numerical and categorical data. You can also use these books:
  8. Deep Learning Intro - Making neural nets uncool again. An awesome Deep learning class from Kaggle Master Jeremy Howard. Entertaining and enlightening at the same time.
Advanced - A series of notes from the Stanford CS class CS231n: Convolutional Neural Networks for Visual Recognition.
Bonus - A free online book by Michael Nielsen.
Advanced Math Book - A math intensive book by Yoshua Bengio &amp;amp; Ian Goodfellow
9. Algorithms, Graph Algorithms, Recommendation Systems, Pagerank and More This course used to be there on Coursera but now only video links on youtube available. You can learn from this book too: 
Apart from that if you want to learn about Python and the basic intricacies of the language you can take the Computer Science Mini Specialization from RICE university too. This is a series of 6 short but good courses. I worked on these courses as Data science will require you to do a lot of programming. And the best way to learn programming is by doing programming. The lectures are good but the problems and assignments are awesome. If you work on this you will learn Object Oriented Programming,Graph algorithms and games in Python. Pretty cool stuff.
10. Advanced Maths: Couldn&amp;rsquo;t write enough of the importance of Math. But here are a few awesome resources that you can go for.
Linear Algebra By Gilbert Strang - A Great Class by a great Teacher. I Would definitely recommend this class to anyone who wants to learn LA.
Multivariate Calculus - MIT OCW
Convex Optimization - a MOOC on optimization from Stanford, by Steven Boyd, an authority on the subject.
The Machine learning field is evolving and new advancements are made every day. That&amp;rsquo;s why I didn&amp;rsquo;t put a third tier. The maximum I can call myself is a &amp;ldquo;Hacker&amp;rdquo; and my learning continues. Hope you do the same.
Hope you like this list. Please provide your inputs in comments on more learning resources as you see fit.
Till then. Ciao!!!
]]>
        
      </content:encoded>
      
      
      
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>